A Guide to the Papers of Carter Glass 1858-1946, and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Personal Correspondence (X-Z) (Box 8)
  A. Correspondence with Woodrow Wilson: Page from a notebook kept by Carter Glass during June, 1919, concerning the possibility of a third term for President Wilson or the nomination of William G. McAdoo. Woodrow Wilson is not felt to be averse to another term. Carter Glass mentions having been asked to take the chairmanship of the Resolutions Committee; April 21, 1918, President Wilson to Carter Glass, asking him to secure immediate passage of the Silver Bill, since war conditions made such legislation imperative; Final page of the Federal Reserve Act, approved on December 23, 1913, with the signature of Woodrow Wilson; Photostats of a note from President Wilson to Carter Glass, accompanying a paper of Samuel Untermeyer, which is to be turned over to William G. McAdoo, after having been read by Carter Glass; Letter, January 9, 1913, from Woodrow Wilson, asking that the currency bill be ready for introduction before the close of the extraordinary session. The President says, "I have had some very interesting conferences about the banking and currency question recently which make it very desirable that I should see you again for a further talk"; January 1, 1913, President Wilson expressing a desire to talk with Carter Glass shortly after Royal Meeker has presented the views of the "members of the Economic Association" to him; President Wilson attempts to arrange a meeting with Carter Glass, April 4, 1912; Letter, June 18, 1913, from Carter Glass, asking that the President change his mind about government control of the Federal Reserve Board, so as to permit banker representation on the board. Carter Glass refers to the agreement of Robert J. Bulkley, "a strong man of the committee with whom we must reckon," an cites the opinion of Bulkley that government control already constituted the real weakness of the measure; Correspondence with Woodrow Wilson, while he was Governor of New Jersey; Copy of a letter, Carter Glass to President Wilson, November 16, 1919, stating that he would prefer to accept an appointment to the Senate, offered by Governor Davis of Virginia, but that, if Woodrow Wilson preferred, he would remain at the Treasury Department; Handwritten copy of a note from Carter Glass to Woodrow Wilson on January 24, 1919, suggesting that John Skelton Williams be reappointed as Comptroller of the Currency, and proposing that Jouett Shouse succeed Love as Assistant Secretary of the Treasury. These suggestions were approved by President Wilson; Resignation of Carter Glass as Secretary of the Treasury, submitted to President Wilson on November 18, 1919, after Wilson had advised acceptance of the appointment to the Senate; In a note, January 29, 1914, President Wilson, having recently spoken with E. D. Hulbert, asks that Carter Glass and Senator Robert L. Owen see what could be done about removing the restriction, inadvertently placed in the currency bill, permitting only national banks to act as reserve agents for a period of three years; Note from Woodrow Wilson on June 20, 1913, thanking Carter Glass for permitting him to see a telegram from E. D. Hulbert, and expressing the hope that Hulbert will change his mind when he sees the actual bill; In a note of May 8, 1913, President Wilson thanks Carter Glass for sending him a copy of "the bill" and promises to consult with him as soon as he has finished working on it; March 23, 1920, Carter Glass presented a recommendation to the President, upon the suggestion of Secretary Houston, that Edmund Platt be appointed to fill a vacant position on the Federal Reserve Board; Secretary to President Wilson writes to Carter Glass on May 24, 1922, to say that the President is anxious to know what Carter Glass has to say about an article by Frank Vanderlip; Newspaper clipping reporting that, before William G. McAdoo resigned from his Treasury post, President Wilson offered Carter Glass an appointment to the Federal Reserve Board; Report of Carter Glass to President Wilson on June 16, 1922, criticizing the plan, intimated by Frank A. Vanderlip, for the creation of an international reserve bank, which Carter Glass considers impractical and unnecessary; Numerous other letters touching upon many subjects.
  B. Correspondence with Clifton A. Woodrum, Congressman from Virginia: Recommendation for assuring true legal tender characteristic for all coin and currency issued by the government, submitted for the approval of Carter Glass by Clifton A. Woodrum; Copy of a letter from a businessman in Roanoke, Virginia, on May 9, 1932, proposing that the world-wide depression would require that the United States reduce its production, until output was more in line with consumption; Copy of a letter sent from a contracting concern to Clifton A. Woodrum on April 30, 1935, regarding a controversy over wages with the Public Works Administration, from which the company had borrowed the money to construct several buildings at the Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Numerous letters relating to a wide variety of national and local problems.
  C. Correspondence with Mrs. Edith Bolling Wilson, wife of Woodrow Wilson: Letter accompanying a portion of the newspaper series, written by Carter Glass in 1926. Carter Glass tells Mrs. Wilson that subsequent installments will relate to the diary of Colonel House and the method of obtaining the Federal Reserve legislation; In a letter, July 14, 1926, Carter Glass tells Mrs. Wilson that her influence was, to some degree, responsible for the rapid acceptance of Charles S. Hamlin as a member of the Federal Reserve Board. Carter Glass states that this appointment was "only thing I have ventured to ask of the present administration;" Considerable personal correspondence between Mrs. Wilson and Carter Glass.
  D. Numerous letter urging Carter Glass to do his best to secure senatorial approval of the entry of the United States into the World Court.
  E. Correspondence with Paul M. Warburg: Highly complimentary letter to Carter Glass from John Wanamaker; Letter, September 14, 1926, Paul M. Warburg expressing the hope that the extension of the charter of the Federal Reserve banks would not be lost in favor of the Hull amendments. Warburg asks that Carter Glass take the opportunity, afforded by his writing a book about the Federal Reserve legislation, to correct some of the misrepresentations contained in the book by H. Parker Willis. Paul M. Warburg states that he does not seek credit for his work in connection with the legislation, but only desires that an account of the history of the measure be presented; In a letter to Paul M. Warburg on October 18, 1926, Carter Glass notes with pleasure the reversal of position by the American Bankers Association on the proposed Hull amendments to the McFadden Bill. Carter Glass refuses to concur in the condemnation by Paul M. Warburg of the H. Parker Willis book, but does feel that certain of the personal attacks, made by H. Parker Willis, were unwarranted. Carter Glass points out that, by his connection with Dr. Edwin R. Seligman, Paul M. Warburg has made himself vulnerable to criticism. Carter Glass feels that he has been as truthful with respect the Paul M. Warburg in his book as he had been regarding Colonel House and Professor Seymour; Letter of April 25, 1930, from Paul M. Warburg, informing Carter Glass that he has found it necessary to submit for public consideration a refutation of certain statements made by Carter Glass and a correction of the numerous misstatements indulged by H. Parker Willis. Warburg expresses continued friendship for Carter Glass and hopes that the public controversy the history of the System quickly dies down, so that attention can be confined to the more important problems, involving saving the System from destruction; Correspondence with Paul M. Warburg in 1929, concerning permission to include two letters, one from Carter Glass to Senator Robert L. Owen and the other from Carter Glass to Paul M. Warburg, in the book which Paul M. Warburg was about to have published; Letter from Carter Glass to H. Parker Willis, marked strictly confidential and dated December 31, 1926. Carter Glass wants to know, whether H. Parker Willis knows anything about the Paul M. Warburg plan for a "Board of Regents," to which Paul M. Warburg has ascribed the origin of the idea for the Federal Reserve Board. Carter Glass continues to defend his position with respect to the origin of this phase of the law, tracing it to President Wilson. Paul M. Warburg feels that Wilson got the idea from him through Colonel House and Morgenthau. Carter Glass reproduces a letter from himself to Paul M. Warburg on this subject; Correspondence relating to the position taken by Carter Glass when the Senate was conducting investigations, under the leadership of Gerald P. Nye, into the part played by Woodrow Wilson in getting the United States into World War I. Carter Glass defended President Wilson.
- Personal and bibliographical correspondence (Box 9)
  A. Remarks by Russell C. Leffingwell on January 4, 1940, upon the presentation of the chair of government at Sweet Briar College, which had been named after Carter Glass; Copies of the Congressional Record for January 8, 1940.
  B. Letters, newspaper clippings, memoranda, and data compiled on the subject of the attempt by the President to pack the Supreme Court; Copy of a speech by Jesse H. Jones, chairman of the Reconstruction Finance Corporation; Copy of an amendment, suggested by Carter Glass, to the law creating the Reconstruction Finance Corporation.
  C. Copy of a report by George N. Peek, head of the Agricultural Adjustment Administration, prepared on September 12, 1933, assigning a high credit rating to the Soviet Union.
  D. Newspaper clippings, relating to the speech by Carter Glass before the Senate on November 1, 1932, in which he attempted to refute the claims of the Hoover Administration that its economic program had been the salvation of the country. Carter Glass charged the Republicans with the responsibility for the depression; Requests for copies of the speech by Carter Glass.
  E. Typewritten copy of speech by Carter Glass, opposing the attempt to pack the Supreme Court.
  F. Photostatic copy of letter to Dr. John L. Newcomb, President of the University of Virginia, from Jesse H. Jones on October 23, 1945, offering to endow a school of international affairs.
  G. Correspondence relating to the candidacy of Carter Glass for re-election to the Senate in 1942.
  H. Several letters congratulating Carter Glass upon his re-election to the Senate in 1942.
- Historical correspondence (Box 10)
  A. Correspondence regarding the purchase by the Federal government of "Red Hill," the home of Patrick Henry; Copies of the act, whereby the Secretary of the Interior was empowered to purchase the Henry estate, and copies of the preliminary bill, introduced by Carter Glass; Correspondence suggesting that Carter Glass support legislation to enshrine Patrick Henry's birthplace in Hanover County, Virginia.
  B. Correspondence involving the Thomas Jefferson Bicentennial Commission; Copies of a bill, introduced by Carter Glass, creating the commission and setting forth its objectives and powers.
- Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 11)
  A. Miscellaneous correspondence: Note of February 26, 1921, from Joseph P. Tumulty, secretary of President Wilson, accompanying an article in which he felt Carter Glass might be interested; Personal note of thanks from Josephus Daniels, Secretary of the Navy; Correspondence concerning war risk insurance.
  B. Miscellaneous correspondence: Note from Joseph P. Tumulty, thanking Carter Glass for sending a letter to the President through him and promising to bring it to Woodrow Wilson's attention; Correspondence with Ray S. Baker concerning the contents of the book Carter Glass was preparing for publication; Photostatic copy of a note to Carter Glass from C. B. Slemp, secretary to the President, on December 13, 1923, expressing regret that Carter Glass disapproves of the "action of the National Committee in regard to Southern representation"; Copy of a report of a joint committee of the Illinois legislature in 1911 on tuberculin tests for cattle; Copy of a letter of November 8, 1912, to Hubert D. Stevens, in which Carter Glass requests support in preventing Samuel Untermeyer from infringing upon the work of the Carter Glass sub-committee, expressing the opinion that there was a connection between Samuel Untermeyer and the Aldrich supporters; Personal note from R. W. Wooley, Director of the Mint, on March 31, 1916; Notes from Richard E. Byrd in 1912; Note of thanks from John Skelton Williams on January 31, 1914.
  C. Miscellaneous and personal letters, relating largely to political affairs: Carter Glass to William C. Bruce on September 20, 1930, promises that he would assist in the effort to have Henry B. Wilcox, a Baltimore banker, appointed to fill the existing vacancy on the Federal Reserve Board; Correspondence relating to a proposed amendment of the Settlement of War Claims Act.
  D. Correspondence with Harold L. Ickes, Secretary of the Interior, largely concerning allocation of scarce resources during World War II: Evidence of a conflict of opinion between Harold L. Ickes and Carter Glass, concerning racial segregation; Letter, May 6, 1936, from Harold L. Ickes, recommending that Carter Glass cast a favorable vote on the question of changing the name of the Interior Department to the Department of Conservation. Harold L. Ickes explains that this move has nothing to do with the proposal, made by Senator Harry F. Byrd, to reorganize the executive branch of the government.
  E. Correspondence with Dr. Hugh G. Young, of Johns Hopkins University, relating largely to legislative matters of a medical nature: Commenting upon an editorial from a Baltimore newspaper on January 17, 1930, listing questions which should be objectively considered by the Carter Glass committee, studying the financial structure of the United States, Dr. Young states that Carter Glass will conduct a thorough investigation in a conservative manner.
- Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 12)
  A. Correspondence with Fred Harper, Lynchburg, Virginia, lawyer.
  B. Correspondence with Samuel M. Kaplan, 1933-1945: Letters, mostly of a personal nature, some dealing with various types of political matters; Correspondence, involving Samuel M. Kaplan, concerning wartime regulation of the prices of woolen goods by the Office of Price Administration; Correspondence relating to legislation affecting the textile industry; Suggestion from Carter Glass that the extension of a loan by the Reconstruction Finance Corporation to a business firm, owned by Samuel M. Kaplan, would be worthy of consideration, honored on November 23, 1936, by the Reconstruction Finance Corporation; March 25, 1933, Carter Glass states that he looked with favor upon suggestion of Samuel M. Kaplan that a National Wool Acceptance Bank be established; Correspondence from Al Kaplan, relating to the economic situation confronting the Franklin D. Roosevelt administration just prior to its accession to control over the federal government. Kaplan was boosting his book, The Solution of the Depression; Copy of the preface of this book is included among the letters sent to Carter Glass; Letter, January 30, 1933, Al Kaplan requests that Carter Glass consider a monetary plan, which he offers as a solution to the economic problems of the depression period; Data regarding Joseph P. Carney, whom Samuel M. Kaplan boosts for a position on the Federal Reserve Board; Letter from Samuel M. Kaplan on March 26, 1934, suggesting that a bill, introduced by Carter Glass, permitting Federal Reserve banks to make capital loans directly to industry, be amended so as to permit Federal Reserve banks to subscribe to stock in any industrial acceptance banks, which might be organized; Criticism by Samuel M. Kaplan of suggested amendments to the Agricultural Adjustment Act, considered valid by Carter Glass; Letter from F. G. Awalt, Acting Comptroller of the Currency, on February 25, 1933, setting forth some of the points upon which further legislation would be necessary with respect to the national banks, if the idea of a National Wool Acceptance Bank were to be put into effect.
  C. Correspondence from Representative Schuyler O. Bland, concerning mostly minor political and legislative matters: Copy of a letter from Schuyler O. Bland to J. T. Garrett, of the Richmond Federal Reserve Bank, asking that the Parksley National Bank, Parksley, Virginia, be permitted to reopen, is sent to Carter Glass with the request that he make a similar appeal on behalf of the community involved; Note from Carter Glass to Schuyler O. Bland on April 18, 1923, accompanying a small copy of an engraving made of Carter Glass while he was Secretary of the Treasury.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence 1902-1942 (Box 13)
  A. General correspondence, not arranged in any particular alphabetical or chronological order: Correspondence from bankers concerning their views on the Federal Reserve Act and their reactions to speeches on this subject by Carter Glass; Clippings of a speech made by Carter Glass at the Constitutional Convention in Norfolk, Virginia; Reproduction of an editorial concerning Louis T. McFadden's views on Investment Trusts, undated; Copy of a speech made by James Connor, Jr., November 23, 1928, regarding Prohibition and failure to support A. Smith; Editorials concerning passage of Federal Reserve Act; Alfred R. Kimball to Secretary William G. McAdoo concerning impression made by Carter Glass at Economics Club dinner and attitude of bankers toward Federal Reserve Act. November 13, 1913; Correspondence between Carter Glass and William G. McAdoo relative to Federal Reserve Act and monetary policies; Letter from Sir George Paish to William G. McAdoo bearing on the gold reserve against Federal Reserve notes; Memorandum from E.R. Black, member of Federal Reserve Board, relative to a study of the commercial and industrial situation in the United States, provisions of legislation enabling the Reserve Banks to make industrial loans, and emphasizing need of small businesses for working capital, undated; Several letters to E. M. Baty and Otis Wingo relative to the Cook County Bankers Association and the "Committee of One Hundred." Letter to Hon. Walter E. Edge regarding possible investigation of lobbying in connection with McFadden Bill; 25 letters betweeen Glass and Dave E. Satterfield; Miscellaneous correspondence with the Hon. P.H. Drewry; Correspondence with Ray Stannard Baker relative to the chapters in his biography of Woodrow Wilson that dealt with the Federal Reserve Act; Telegram from Huey Long setting forth his ideas on "scarcity of production" as a solution to the South's economic problems; Portion of letter to Senator Copper regarding monetization of debt in World War I; Copy of a report of Frederick A. Delano on the subject of clearing, 1915; Correspondence with President Woodrow Wilson, 1919; Letter to President Harding from Comptroller of the Currency, 1920, recommending a certain amendment to the Federal Reserve Act; Letter from Carter Glass to H. Parker Willis, 1912, regarding Samuel Untermeyer and Pujo, second page missing.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence 1912-1913 (Box 14)
  A. General correspondence, apparently not filed in any systematic fashion, pertaining primarily to political appointments and elections in Virginia: Requests for bulletins, seeds, etc.; Bills; Receipts; Personal letters.
  B. Of special interest are the following: Letter from George Roberts to Carter Glass, 1913, expressing his views on the problem of gold reserves for the Reserve Banks; Letter from Laurence A. Murray, Comptroller, advising certain administrative reforms in National Bank Act, 1913; Editorials on monetary and currency problems; Letter from G. J. Frame relative to his opinions on the proposed currency legislation. February 10, 1913.
- Correspondence 1912-1916 (Box 15)
  A. Miscellaneous correspondence, not filed in any systematic order, covering mainly requests for favors, the election of 1912, and appointments in Virginia.
  B. Of interest are the following: Copies of several House bills referred to Carter Glass' subcommittee for consideration in 1912; Several addresses on the subject of banking; 3 typed sheets analyzing present banking situation and suggesting reform, undated and unsigned; Explanatory statement regarding "The Currency Reform Bill" by Harlow H. Chamberlain, and copy of bill; Letter from Carter Glass to Alexander Moyer of the New York Evening Post concerning origin of Federal Reserve Act; Letter to John Gavit, "Evening Post," regarding origin of Federal Reserve Act; Reprints from various Chambers of Commerce endorsing the Morris plan.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence 1913 (Box 16)
  A. Advance copy of the speech by Carter Glass to the House of Representatives in 1913, reporting the Currency Bill out of committee; Note from Joseph P. Tumulty, Secretary to President Wilson, mentioning Andrew; Notes from William G. McAdoo, Secretary of the Treasury, one of which concerns a redraft of a proposed amendment and a handwritten suggestion that Carter Glass consult Hayes, before taking any action; Letter from Woodrow Wilson on August 6, 1912, concerning campaign plans; Copy of the bill introduced in the House of Representatives in 1913 by Carter Glass and referred to the Banking and Currency Committee, attached is a list of nine reasons for considering the bill at the extra session of Congress; List of proposed amendments and the reason for the changes suggested; Lengthy statement from Frank Vanderlip of National City Bank on July 24, 1913, concerning the banking system and proposed reforms; Letter of July 7, 1913, from George N. Reynolds, of the Chicago Continental and Commercial National Bank, concerning reserve requirements and the creation of an Advisory Board; Handwritten copy of a speech Carter Glass had prepared for delivery before the House of Representatives, concerning the credit for the authorship of the Federal Reserve Act, particularly refuting the claim that the work of Senator Nelson W. Aldrich was largely responsible for the content of the Federal Reserve Act; Letter, April 13, 1917, by Paul M. Warburg, as a member of the Federal Reserve Board, requesting that state banks be permitted to hold reserve balances at the Federal Reserve Banks; Report from the Governor of the Federal Reserve Board addressed to Senator Robert L. Owen, defending the system of check clearing against elimination; Copy of a resolution, passed by the Governors of the Federal Reserve banks, opposing the Kitchen bill, which would permit the collection of exchange charges by national banks; Note from Joseph P. Tumulty, Secretary to the President, regarding examinations for entrance into the Naval Academy; Letter presents a question concerning the definition of "gold or lawful money" in the Currency Bill; Letter, August 5, 1913, approving a provision for the distribution of 40% of the surplus earnings among the banks according to their reserve balances; Letter of August 6, 1913, from a branch of the American Bankers Association, urging recognition of savings departments in National Banks; Letter, August 4, 1913, from a bank in Flint, Michigan, suggesting certain changes in the proposed currency legislation; Statement of opposition to the Glass-Owen bill under consideration by Congress during the summer of 1913; Letter, July 31, 1913, from the Solicitor of the Treasury, suggesting a few changes in the Currency Bill, having been requested to comment upon the measure; Telegram from Sol Wexler, August 6, 1913, requesting a draft of the bill as approved by the committee; Telegram, August 6, 1913, inquiring as to the possibility of making further changes in phraseology before the caucus meeting. William W. Flannagan sent the telegram; Letters touching upon the bill being prepared by Carter Glass; Copies of the amended banking and currency measure are requested; Letters from Robert D. Kent, President of the Merchants Bank of Passaic, New Jersey, suggesting changes in the tax on currency issue and questioning the possibility of acquiring emergency currency under the Aldrich-Vreeland Act; Letter from the president of the Craddock-Terry shoe concern in Lynchburg, Virginia, suggesting the amendment of the Aldrich-Vreeland Act, reducing the rate of interest; Letter, August 6, 1913, from H. Parker Willis to Carter Glass, stating that minor changes in wording were all that remained to accomplish in creating satisfactory legislation; Voting on the bill is noted, H. Parker Willis expresses displeasure with certain amendments, which he understands to have been made, he feels that it is very important to finish a report, upon which he is working, and a gives a progress report to Carter Glass; Confidential correspondence, May 27, 1913, from Senator Robert L. Owen to Carter Glass, enclosing a copy of a bill for currency reform suggested by Robert L. Owen, mentions having discussed his bill with H. Parker Willis and having criticized the Willis draft. Robert L. Owen lists the general changes, which he feels must be made to get the Willis plan into acceptable form; Letter from the president of the Northern Trust Company of Chicago, expressing favor for the proposed measure and stating that changes he would suggest would be very minor; Boston Evening Transcript, Saturday April 19, 1913, lauding the provision of the Carter Glass bill making it possible for national banks to establish foreign branches; Newspaper article on the day of the Federal Reserve Act, recalling the earliest meeting of Carter Glass and Wilson regarding currency reform; Letter, July 17, 1913, to Carter Glass from Charles S. Hamlin, which states that a memorandum suggesting changes in the Currency Bill is enclosed; Letter, January 23, 1914, from a depositor of a failed bank, protesting the practice of permitting persons responsible for the failure to engage in the task of putting the bank back on its feet; Letter from the president of the Merchants Loan and Trust Company in Chicago, requesting that the state banks be put on approximately the same footing as national banks under the new legislation; Copies of an amendment proposed by Hammer.